A Guide to the Theresa Pollak Papers 1917-1996
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Theresa Pollak Papers 1917-1996
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 5
9 linear feet
Theresa Pollak
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is available for research.
Acquisition Information
Provenance: Donated to the Special Collections and Archives Department by Miss Pollak in 1971, 1974, 1976, 1977, 1986, 1987, 1989, 1990, 1994 and 1996.
Biographical/Historical Information
Theresa Pollak (1899-2002) was one of Virginia's most well-known artists and art educators. She was instrumental in the founding of Virginia Commonwealth University's School of the Arts. A native of Richmond, Virginia, Pollak was a nationally recognized painter whose art works have been exhibited in institutions as the Whitney Museum of American Art in New York, the Museum of Fine Art in Boston, and the Corcoran Gallery in Washington, D. C. More importantly, Pollak is credited with the introduction of modern art to Richmond.
Born 13 August 1899, Pollak graduated from Westhampton College of the University of Richmond. In 1920 she was accepted at the Art Students League of New York, and with the support of Dr. Orie Latham Hatcher, who helped her get a tuition scholarship, she was able to continue her work at the League after graduating from Westhampton in 1921. During Pollak's stay in New York, one of her drawings was awarded the first prize at the Studio club of New York (1926). She continued her training with post-graduate work at the Fogg Museum of Harvard University, and later she studied at the Hans Hoffmann School of Painting in Provincetown, Massachusetts.
In 1928 Pollak became the first full time art teacher at Richmond Professional Institute (RPI), at that time a division of William and Mary College. Two years later she also helped start an art program at Westhampton College. In 1935 she began teaching full time at RPI and devoted much of her other time to her own work. A year after RPI merged in 1968 with the Medical College of Virginia to become Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU), Pollak retired from the school. In 1971, the newly completed fine arts building on what is now the Monroe Park campus of VCU was named in her honor. Her forty-one year teaching career influenced generations of Virginia artists.
A noted Virginia artist with paintings in the permanent collections of the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, the University of Virginia, Mary Baldwin College, and in numerous private collections, Pollak's paintings are part of the Permanent Research Collection at Virginia Commonwealth University's Anderson Gallery. She died at the age of 103 on 18 September 2002.
Scope and Content Information
The Theresa Pollak Papers consists of materials covering Miss Pollak's academic and artistic career from 1917 to 1988 (primarily 1940s-1980s). Of particular note are the materials and correspondence Miss Pollak gathered about her major instructors influencing her artistic work, Allen Tucker and Hans Hoffmann. Also included in the collection are Christmas cards designed by Miss Pollak's former students and fellow faculty members and photographs of Miss Pollak's work and from her 1986 exhibit at the Anderson Gallery. A collection of slides of T. Pollak's works are available in box 20.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by series and alphabetically therein.
Organization
Organized into the following seven series:
I. Personal Materials, 1931-1986
II. Correspondence, 1938-1987
III. Richmond Professional Institute and Virginia Commonwealth University, 1946-1975
IV. Artistic Career, 1928-1976
V. Photographs
VI. Year Books, 1917-1921
VII. Oversize Materials
Contents List
- Series I--Personal Material
  - Biographical Data and Resumes 1973-1988 (Box 1)
  - Cards for Theresa Pollak's 80th Birthday 1979 (Box 1)
  - Cards for Theresa Pollak's 93rd Birthday 1992 (Box 1)
  - Date Books and Address Books 1969-1986 (Box 1)
  - Federated Arts Council of Richmond 1976 (Box 1)
  - Letters written by T. Pollak from Europe, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Personal Notes (T.P.) 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Personal Notes (T.P.) 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Personal Notes (T.P.) 1951-1968 (Box 1)
  - Reynolds-Minor Gallery, n.d. 1982 (Box 1)
  - Material from visit to France 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - European Trip 1962 (Box 1)
  - Scott-McKennis Gallery (Box 1a)
  - Thompson Street Studio (Box 1a)
  - Virginia Cultural Laureate Center (Box 1a)
  - Who's Who (Box 1a)
  - Women's Resource Center (Box 1a)
  - Writings by T.P. 1975 (Box 1a)
  - Writings by T.P. Miscellaneous 1931-1971 (Box 1a)
- Series II--Correspondence
  - Correspondence: Building Dedication 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Institutions--VCU 1978-1983 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Institutions VCU 1984-1994 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Institutions Virginia Museum 1969-1987 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Friends A-L not otherwise listed 1938-1989 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Friends A-L not otherwise listed 1992-1994 (Box 2a)
  - Correspondence: Friends M-Z not otherwise listed 1938-1989 (Box 2a)
  - Correspondence: Friends M-Z not otherwise listed 1992-1994 (Box 2a)
  - Correspondence: Friends M-Z not otherwise listed 1992-1994 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Archer, Edmund 1981-1986 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Barnet, Elena and Will, n.d. 1959 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Behl, Wolfgang (Ted), n.d. 1953-1984 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Benson, Evelyn 1987 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Blaine, Nell 1943-1989, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Blanton, Jack, n.d. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Bonds, Maurice 1946-1995 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Bonds, Maurice (re: Pollak Retirement) 1969 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Boomer, Canan and Jim 1984-1989 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Boyd, Julie 1977-1982 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Bright, George 1977 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Bryan, John, n.d. 1986-1995 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Bryan, John 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Campbell, Lawrence 1973-1980 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Corporation 1934 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Chappell, Warren 1969-1980, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Cheek, Mary Tyler 1953 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Clark, Adele, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Cossitt, Dick and Mary 1964, 1969, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Cox, Adeline, n.d. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Cunningham, Jean/Hall, Frank 1986 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Day, Worden 1946-1983 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Eisenhart, Lucy, n.d. 1969, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Evans, May 1969, 1971, 1986-1987 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Evans, Xantha 1978-1988 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Evans, Xantha 1985-1994 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Family, n.d. 1956-1993 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Family--Gallant, Sara P. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Family-Pollak, Philip (Brother) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Family-Pollak, Philip (Cousin) (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Family-Reiser, Eugene, n.d. 1977-1989 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Gerst, Elsa Wallerstein, n.d. 1956-1986 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Gladding, Jane Bell, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Gwathmey, Mary Stuart, n.d. 1980 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Hanneman, Bodil, n.d. 1984, 1991-1993 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Hellman, Eith and Charles Madison 1949-1984, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Hinter-Reiter, Gilda, n.d. 1969-1973 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Girose, Naoe Kondo 1971-1985 (Box 5)
  - Hodges, Sophia (Su) 1973-1983, 1992 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Lons, Willoughby, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Johnson, Julie (Lily) 1977, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Jones, Bob and Flo, n.d. 1993 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Jones, Louise, n.d. 1951-1986 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Jones, Mary (Mrs. Sherwood), n.d. 1981-1987, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Jones, Theresa, n.d. 1988 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Kirkpatrick, Mary Jane, n.d. 1950-1992 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Kohler, Winfield 1973, 1975, 1983-1990, 1992-1993 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Lazaron, Edna Sara, n.d. 1990 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Leback, Chloe (Debbie Lang Ittner), n.d. 1978-1988, 1991-1994 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Leyden, Flora Hutzler, n.d. 1962-1987 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Lichtenstein, Alice 1973-1977 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Lockey, Savannah Cross 1971, 1978 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Lu Pau, Faye Purdy, n.d. 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: McDowell, Charles 1982 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Morenus, Constance, n.d. 1972-1985 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Nemuth, Harold 1982-1984 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Nichols, Baylor 1960-1969 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Ninetieth Birthday 1989 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Norris, Ruby Lee 1967 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Pole, Frank N. 1981 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Pollard, Violet McD. 1972 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Reschofsky, Jean 1982, 1985 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Russell, Milo, n.d. 1978-1987, 1992-1993 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Russi, Gertrude 1961-1970 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Ryan, Dinah J. 1981-1985 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Savage, Anne 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Sibley, Charles 1983 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Smith, Charles 1934-1976 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Stern, Adele, n.d. 1988 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Sympathy on Brother's Death 1980 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Thalhimer, n.d. 1973, 1986 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Tiffany Foundation 1932 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Torres,s John 1982 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Troubetzkoy, Ulrich 1969, 1986-1988 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Tyler, Betty Sessler, n.d. 1955-1990, 1992, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Van Nortwick, Ramona, n.d. 1973, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Winfree, R. Westwood 1969-1970, 1980, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Christmas Cards--Friends not otherwise listed (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: Former Students not otherwise listed, A-Z 1956-1986 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Abrams, Ross, n.d. 1950, 1956, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Alexick, David, n.d. 1969, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Bogart, Harriet, n.d. 1969-1984 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Bumpas, Rosemary 1970-1973 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Campbell, Jeanne, n.d. 1960-1988, 1991 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Carlyon, Richard, n.d. 1954 (Box 8)
  - Davenport, Susan, n.d. 1969, 1983 (Box 8)
  - Davidson, Nerida 1974-1982 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Davis, Alice Downing, n.d. 1968-1985, 1993 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Freeman, G. Mallory, n.d. 1969, 1974-1975 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Green, Margaret, n.d. 1960-1978, 1988, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Hooper, Bill, n.d. 1972, 1988, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Houchens, Douglas, n.d. 1975, 1982, 1988, 1991-1993 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Huf, Turid, n.d. 1965 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Kemp, Margaret Stark, n.d. 1949-1971, 1988 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Kennedy, Barbara, n.d. 1964-1981 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: Kennedy, Lori/Bassett, Mark 1989-1990 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Kesler, Sally, n.d. 1955, 1971, 1978, 1988, 1993 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Kesler, Sally- Linen Prints (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Kiermaier, Constance, n.d. 1982, 1986 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Land, Sarah Riley, n.d. 1969-1971 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Lorvig, Toni Kutyna, n.d. 1966-1987, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Lyne, Ann, n.d. 1959-1988 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Lyne, Ann 1989-1990, 1991-1993 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Moorman, Jackie, n.d. 1977-1983, 1993 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Morgan, Catherine (Moomaw), n.d. 1950-1989 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Morse, Marsden Gresham, n.d. 1977-1984 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Oakley, Thomas 1969, 1984, 1986, 1989-1991, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Quattlebaum, Lou Godfrey, n.d. 1977, 1982, 1991 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Rex, Frances 1969-1987, 1992 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: Rice, Anthony (Tony and Linda) 1967-1976 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Robertson, Catherine, n.d. 1966-1982 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Rowe, Kenneth and Kitty 1992-1993 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Smiley, Kathryn, n.d. 1982, 1988 (Box 10)
  - Smith, Ashlin Wyatt, n.d. 1955-1980 (Box 10)
  - Springer, Homer, n.d. 1966-1988, 1992-1993 (Box 10)
  - Stevens, Barry, n.d. 1974-1980 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Stevens, Barry, n.d. 1974-1980 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Stuart, Frances Bear 1989 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Turner, Ted 1959, 1985, 1988, 1990 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Vassar, Karen, n.d. 1986, 1988, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Webb, Muriel Navarro, n.d. 1972-1986 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: Wright, Willie Ann, n.d. 1969-1991 (Box 10)
  - Christmas cards from former students and faculty not otherwise listed, A-Z (Box 10)
  - Correspondence (unsorted) 1979-1995 (Box 10a)
- Series III--Richmond Professional Institute and Virginia Commonwealth University
  - Material About former Students 1975 (Box 11)
  - Material on former Students 1965- (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Class Lecture Notes, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Class Lecture Notes, n.d. (Box 11)
  - Notes for Lectures 1974 (Box 11)
  - References, n.d. (Box 11)
  - References 1952-1964 (Box 11)
  - References 1960 (Box 11)
  - References 1969-1987 (Box 11)
  - Retirement Mailing List 1969 (Box 12)
  - Reunion class of 1938 (Box 12)
  - The League Quarterly 1946-1949 (Box 12)
  - Typed Working Copy of Reminiscences 1948, 1968 (Box 12)
  - VCU Self Study Report 1964 (Box 12)
  - Cap and Gown for Honorary Doctorate (Box 12a)
  - Cultural Laureate Medallion 1977 (Box 12a)
- Series IV--Artistic Career
  - Art Criticism for local paper, n.d. 1931 (Box 12b)
  - Catalogues of exhibitions involving Theresa Pollak 1927-1939 (Box 12b)
  - Catalogues of exhibitions involving Theresa Pollak 1940-1949 (Box 12b)
  - Catalogues of exhibitions involving Theresa Pollak 1950-1959 (Box 12b)
  - Catalogues of exhibitions involving Theresa Pollak 1960-1979 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: exhibitions 1928-1959 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: exhibitions 1960-1969 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: exhibitions, n.d. 1967-1979 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: Anderson Gallery exhibit 1986 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: Anderson Gallery exhibit/YWCA Award 1986 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: RWCA Award 1992 (Box 13)
  - F and M Bank Art Acquisition Committee 1973-1974 (Box 13)
  - Hans Hoffman, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Hans Hoffman 1958 (Box 14)
  - Hans Hoffman 1964 (Box 14)
  - Boris Margo 1947 (Box 14)
  - Notes and Articles on Art Subjects, n.d. (Box 14)
  - News Clippings 1928-1955 (Box 14)
  - News Clippings 1956-1968 (Box 14)
  - News Clippings 1969-1976 (Box 14)
  - News Clippings-Miscellaneous 1973 (Box 14)
  - News Clippings, n.d. 1986-1988 (Box 14)
  - News Clippings-Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 14)
  - One Woman Exhibit 1977 (Box 14)
  - Plans for Retrospective exhibit 1969 (Box 14)
  - Printed Material about Theresa Pollak, n.d. 1932
  - Printed Material about Theresa Pollak 1977-1993 (Box 15)
  - Printed Material about Theresa Pollak, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Printed Material about Theresa Pollak, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Slide lists and notes, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Clyfford Still 1969 (Box 15)
  - Text-Radio Talk 1940 (Box 15)
  - Text-Radio Discussion, n.d. (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials re: Allen Tucker 1939, 1967 (Box 16)
  - Article, portfolio re: Allen Tucker, n.d. (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials 1986-1987, 1991 (Box 16)
  - Invitations to judge, attend exhibit openings 1975-1988 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence re: sold and donated paintings 1957-1988 (Box 16)
  - Research inquiries from students 1973-1985 (Box 16)
  - Who's Who in Jewelry information 1978-1980 (Box 16)
  - Publications and Pamphlets about Pollak and her work, n.d. (Box 16a)
    1939, 1955, 1964, 1966, 1969, 1973, 1978, 1989
- Series V--Photographs
  - Afton Mountains 1961 (Box 17)
  - Anderson Gallery Opening (Retrospective 1986) (Box 17)
  - Aunt Martha Tucker 1935 (Box 17)
  - Aunt Martha's Hands 1935 (Box 17)
  - Autumn II 1965 (Box 17)
  - Blue Figure 1960 (Box 17)
  - Chrysanthemums for Tea 1939 (Box 17)
  - Cityscape with Figure ca. 1954 (Box 17)
  - Corsage (Box 17)
  - Crucial Moment 1957 (Box 17)
  - Dedication of Pollak Building (Box 17)
  - Far From the Maddening Crowd 1939 (Box 17)
  - Grace Street in the spring 1951 (Box 17)
  - Grove Avenue Studio (Box 17)
  - Head of a Child 1960 (Box 17)
  - Head of a Girl ca. 1953 (Box 17)
  - Joint Exhibit (Pollak and Bonds) 1960 (Box 17)
  - Look of My Studio Wall 1968 (Box 17)
  - Maude Woodfin's Mother 1941 (Box 17)
  - Meeting in the Park 1945 (Box 17)
  - Metro 1963 (Box 17)
  - Mountain Lake 1960 (Box 17)
  - Mountain Sketch 1940 (Box 17)
  - Mrs. Cimbalo (Box 17)
  - Nature Madness 1963 (Box 17)
  - New York Exhibition Opening 1930s (Box 17)
  - On Deck 1964 (Box 17)
  - Parade 1945 (Box 17)
  - Pier 1955 (Box 17)
  - Piney Grove 1944 (Box 17)
  - Pollak Family (Box 17)
  - Pollak Family-Immediate (Box 17)
  - Pollak Friends (Box 17)
  - Pollak Homes (Box 17)
  - Pollak-Martha's Vineyard (Box 17)
  - Pollak-Tiffany Foundation (Box 17)
  - Pussy Willows 1930 (Box 17)
  - Red Line of Growth 1968 (Box 17)
  - Reverie 1960 (Box 17)
  - Reverie in a Garden 1958 (Box 17)
  - River 1967 (Box 17)
  - Rural and Marine 1937 (Box 17)
  - Seaside Lawn 1955 (Box 17)
  - Sixth Street Market 1940 (Box 17)
  - Southern Kitchen 1924 (Box 17)
  - Square du vert galaute 1962 (Box 17)
  - Still Life with Seckel Pear ca. 1941 (Box 17)
  - Studio Interior 1952 (Box 17)
  - Studio Table 1966 (Box 17)
  - Studio Visit 1931 (Box 17)
  - Studio Wall 1960-1974 (Box 17)
  - Sumac 1931 (Box 17)
  - Summer Idyll 1955 (Box 17)
  - Summer Outing 1960 (Box 17)
  - Sunflowers 1951 (Box 17)
  - Theresa Pollak French Friend Lily (Box 17)
  - Tracery of winter 1960 (Box 17)
  - Two Heads 1960 (Box 17)
  - Two Women 1963 (Box 17)
  - View from Gambles Hill, Richmond 1965 (Box 17)
  - Voices 1941 (Box 17)
  - Warm Springs Mountain 1940 (Box 17)
  - Widow 1933 (Box 17)
  - William Gray 1929 (Box 17)
- Series VI--Years Books 1917-1921
  - Yearbooks 1917-1918, 1921 (Box 18)
  - Film (Box 18)
  - Correspondence: Edumund M. Archer 1932-1969 (Box 19)
    Restricted
  - Correspondence: Harriet Bogart 1961-1972 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence: Allen and Efrasia Tucker 1923-1939 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence: R.P.I. 1928-1937 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence: R.P.I. 1938-1960 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence: VCU 1961 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence: Westhampton College/University of Richmond 1930-1974 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence: Virginia Museum 1937-1974 (Box 19)
  - Class Roll 1967-1969 (Box 19)
  - Collection of slides of T. Pollak's works (Box 20)
- Series VII--Oversize Materials
  - Diplomas, Certificates and Awards, n.d. 1913-1979, oversized (Oversize 17.1)
  - Wall panels (text and photographs)from the Theresa Pollak and Milo Russell exhibition 1973, oversized (Oversize 17.2)
  - Exhibition Posters, oversized (Oversize 17.3)
  - Commemorative Poster of Theresa Pollak's 100th Birthday August 13, 1999, oversized (Oversize 17.4)
  - Sketches (by Jewett?), oversized (Oversize 17.5)
  - Photograph of Pollak in studio, signed by J.O.F. Jr 1948, oversized (Oversize 17.6)